TIAGO ROMERO GARCIA

San Francisco, CA

SUMMARY

Front-end architect with 12 years of experience in full-stack software development, software architecture, web performance, technical leadership and agile methodologies. Acted as an evangelist for good practices, code quality, unit tests and team synergy, through servant leadership. Mentored individuals and trained entire teams with diverse skill sets in front-end, back-end, leadership and agile practices.

SKILLS AND HIGHLIGHTS

Strong in JavaScript, CSS, Node.js, React, Redux, Marionette.js, Backbone.js, Jasmine, Webpack, Java, Spring, Git, Unit Tests, Performance, Design Patterns, Responsive Design.

Published more than a dozen articles in renowned websites and magazines such as InfoQ, DZone, Medium, Dev.to, AirPair and Java Magazine.

Spoke at several major conferences internationally, such as ForwardJS, FEDC, Abstractions, DevCon5 and HTML5DevConf, as well as in meetups and corporate trainings in San Francisco and New York. Organized the Backbone.js meetup in San Francisco.

EXPERIENCE

Front-end Architect and Tech Manager | Avenue Code | San Francisco, CA JULY 2010 - PRESENT

- Started the branch in Brazil as its first employee, assuming the roles of Software Engineer,
 Tech Lead and Tech Manager. In the first 4 years, I led the growth to 120 employees in 3 offices in Belo Horizonte and São Paulo.
- After moving to the US in 2014, support our clients with architectural design, technology evaluation and adoption, consultancy, coding and trainings, as well as managing and mentoring engineers.

Tech Lead | Sephora | San Francisco, CA

FEBRUARY 2018 - PRESENT

- Lead a team which develops and deliver innovative new features such as Guest Checkout, which achieved 35% increased signups for the loyalty program and 5% lift in conversion in the first weeks after launch, and expects \$30 Million increase in annual revenue. The team is using React, Redux, ES7, Node.js, Jasmine and Sinon.
- Organize, guide and provide the team with their needs, while coordinating all the work with Product Managers, UX, Tech leads from other teams and Architects, while taking design and architectural decisions, specially around A/B testing strategy.

Tech Lead | Macys | San Francisco, CA

FEBRUARY 2014 - JANUARY 2018

- Architected and orchestrated the implementation of a modernized Product Details Page: fully responsive, universally rendered (isomorphic), with a loosely-coupled component-based architecture, consuming microservices and lazy-loading components not needed during the page load, using Marionette.js, Handlebars, ES6 and Node.js
- Results: \$150 Million increase in annual revenue, 50% reduction in the page load time, 80% reduction in the speed index, while close to 100% in unit test coverage.

Tech Lead | Walmart | Alphaville, Brazil

FEBRUARY 2013 - JANUARY 2014

- Designed and led the implementation of a brand new Customer Service single-page application using Backbone.js, Handlebars and Underscore, consuming REST webservices written in Ruby on Rails.
- Spearheaded the implementation of the redesigned My Account page from Walmart's new site launch, when it became the first Brazilian company with 100% uptime during the period between black friday and cyber monday, surpassing the revenue target in 50%.

Senior Full-stack Software Engineer | Macys | San Francisco, CA

AUGUST 2010 - JANUARY 2013

- Developed several features across the website, while advocating for coding standards and better performance, by measuring and fixing issues found with YSlow.
- Detected and fixed a major memory leak present on almost every Selenium test case, reducing the overall memory footprint in about 30%.

EDUCATION

Postgraduate in Distributed Systems Architecture | PUC Minas | Belo Horizonte, Brazil AUGUST 2011 - DECEMBER 2012

B.S. in Computer Science (summa cum laude) | UNIFEI | Itajuba, Brazil

FEBRUARY 2004 - DECEMBER 2008

AWARDS AND CERTIFICATIONS

First Prize on AirPair's 2015 Developer Writing Competition - JUNE 2015

Certified "Programming in HTML5 with JavaScript and CSS3" by Microsoft - FEBRUARY 2013

Certified "Sun Certified Web Component Developer for the Java 2 Platform, Enterprise Edition 5.0 (SCWCD)" by Sun Microsystems - DECEMBER 2008

Certified "Sun Certified Programmer for the Java 2 Platform, Standard Edition 5.0 (SCJP)" by Sun Microsystems - FEBRUARY 2006